(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-18T00:59:57.682752",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": false,
"max_retries_exceeded": true,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.8-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
みなさーん、こんばんはー！ハロー！
Good evening, everyone! Hello!
こんばんは！ / Selamat malam!
Good evening! / Selamat malam!
はーい！ということで、まず自己紹介からやっていきましょう！
All right! So, let's start with our self-introductions!
ホロライブの清楚担当、みんなのアイドルの夏色まつりです！
I'm hololive's purity representative, everyone's idol, Natsuiro Matsuri!
今日はMC、お願いします。頑張りまーす！
I'm your host today. I'll do my best!
じゃあ、今日参加してくださる人たち一人ずつ行きますよ。
Now then, let's go one by one with today's participants.
じゃあヨピピからお願いします！
Yopipi, please go first!
はい！イオフォリア、オビサ！どうもです！ホロライブインドネシアからイオフィです！
Yes! Ioforia, obisa! Hello, I'm Iofi from hololive Indonesia!
今日はオノマトペを、ちょっと...
Today, about onomatopoeia... a little...
可愛い。
Cute.
のことちょっと、勉強したいと思います！よろしくお願いします！
I'd like to study about that today! Nice to meet you!
お願いしまーす！
Nice to have you!
じゃあ、こぼちゃん！
Next up, Kobo-chan!
ワカワカワカ... Kobo Kanaeru at your service! Let me be your sun to shine your day, ahem!
Waka waka waka... Kobo Kanaeru at your service! Let me be your sun to shine your day, ahem!
コボ・カナエル、レイン・シャーマンです！
I'm Kobo Kanaeru, the rain shaman!
今日はオノマトペア、勝ちだ！お願いします！
Today, for onomatopoeia... ah, I'll win! Please take care of me!
頑張ろう！
Let's do this!
じゃあ、続いてジジ！
All right, next up is Gigi!
こんばんは！ジジです！ちむにん...
Good evening! I'm Gigi! A chimeranian...
えーっと、日本語ちょっと、上手じゃない。
Um, my Japanese is a bit... not that good.
オノマトペ、ちょっと、日本語を頑張って！
Onomatopoeia... I'll do my best with Japanese!
頑張ります！
I'll do my best!
ありがとー！頑張れー！
Thank you! Do your best!
はい！じゃあ続いて、ほぼJPのベっちゃん！
All right! Next is Bae-chan, who's basically JP!
いやいや、What's up? 我らはChaos！ホロライブのハコス・ベールズです！
No no no. What's up? We are Chaos! I'm Hakos Baelz from hololive!
今日は翻訳担当でやりたいと思います！よろしくお願いしまーす！
Today, I'll be handling the translations! Looking forward to working with you!
お願いしまーす！
Looking forward to it!
はい、じゃあ最後、ラオラー！
Yes! And finally, Raora!
あ、こんにちはー！ラオラ・パンテーラです！
Ah, hello! I'm Raora Panthera!
今日は、絵を描いたり、日本語で話したり、頑張りまっそう！
Today, I'll draw pictures, speak in Japanese, and do my best!
はーい、お願いしまーす！
Yes, let's do this!
はい！ということでね、本日はですね、皆さんにオノマトペクイズに答えてもらいます！
All right! So today, everyone will be answering an onomatopoeia quiz!
ちょっとね、日本独特の表現とかもたくさんあるんですが、頑張って答えてね。
There are plenty of expressions unique to Japan, but give it your best shot!
ぜひね、日本に来る際はいっぱい使っていただきたいなと思います！
Whenever you visit Japan, I really hope you'll get to use them a lot!
はい、ということで！早速第1問いきましょう！
All right, without further ado, let's move on to Question 1!
Question one!
First question!
このオノマトペは何を表しているでしょうか？
What does this onomatopoeia represent?
「コケコッコー」
\"Cock-a-doodle-doo\" [Kokekokko].
What's this? What's the sound of... / コケコッコー。
What's this? What's the sound of... / Kokekokko.
Where do you hear this onomatopoeia from? Onomatopoeia... / Poeeea?
ああ、わからない！
Ah, I have no idea!
わからない場合どうします？
What do we do if we don't know?
あ、じゃあヒントは、動物の鳴き声ですね！何の動物の鳴き声でしょうか？
Well, the hint is: it's an animal call! What kind of animal call is it?
It's an animal cry! What animal makes...
Error processing subtitles for this segment.
キメラ？
A chimera?
Oh my god.
キマイラ言うのやめて？
Stop calling it a chimera.
ほいじゃあ、ちょっと一人ずつまた聞いていきますか？
Alright then, shall we ask everyone one by one again?
かわいい、みんな。
Everyone's is so cute.
えー、じゃあ、よぴぴ。
Okay, first up, Yopipi.
はい！カエルです！Frogです！
Yes! It's a frog! A frog!
あー！Frog！ケロ、ケロケロでしょ？
Ah! Frog! Ribbit, it goes "kero kero", right?
なるほど。
I see.
カエルね！
はい！はい！
A frog, then!
Yes! Yes!
じゃあ、続いてこぼちゃん。
Alright, next up, Kobo-chan.
あたしも、かえ...カエル？カエル、Frog！
Me too... a fr... frog? Frog, frog!
Frog！カエル！はい、ケロケロ。
Frog! A frog! Yes, ribbit ribbit.
漢字で書いてる！すごーい！
She wrote it in kanji! Amazing!
まつりも書けないよ、蛙。
Even Matsuri can't write that kanji for frog.
はい、じゃあ続いてジジ！
Alright, next up, Gigi!
はい！ケロケロ！けろっぴ！
Yes! Kero kero! Keroppi!
あ、けろけろけろっぴ！おー！なるほどー！
Ah, Kero Kero Keroppi! Oh, I see!
じゃあ、べーちゃん！
Alright, Bae-chan!
あ、カエルです！
Ah, it's a frog!
お？カエルかな？
カエルです！
Oh? Is that a frog?
It's a frog!
カエル？
A frog?
カエル！
Frog!
カエル...一瞬ちょっとね...
A frog... for a second...
一瞬ネズミに見えたんだけどね。
it kind of looked like a rat for a moment, though.
いや、ちょっと...さすがにね、カエル見たことないんで...
Well, lately... I haven't seen a frog, so...
一応カエル。画伯だ。
A frog, supposedly. A true artist.
その隣の、えーラオラ！めっちゃ絵上手い！
And next to her, Raora! Your drawing is so good!
かわいい！
Cute!
Yay!
はい、カエルですね？
Alright, so that's a frog, right?
うん！カエルです！
Yep! It's a frog!
はい！じゃあ「ケロケロ」、正解は...
Yes! Then for "kero kero", the correct answer is...
「カエル」でございます！
...a frog!
イェーイ！正解！やったー！
Yay! Correct! Hurray!
Nice, nice, yeah!
Easy! Easy! Easy!
やったー！簡単だった！
Hurray! That was so easy!
日本語上手！
Good Japanese!
日本語上手よ！
Your Japanese is so good!
ねー！
Yeah!
じゃ、続いて行きますよ。
Alright, moving on to the next one.
続いては、えー、こちら！
Next up is... this!
馬の鳴き声は？日本だと何と言うでしょう？
"What sound does a horse make?" What do they say in Japan?
What sound does a horse make?
馬ね。
A horse.
Japanese onomatopoeia.
分からなーい！
I don't know!
何て言うの？
What do they say?
何て聞こえるかな？何て聞こえるかなー？
How does it sound to you? What does it sound like?
うーん...
Hmm...
Mimi...
イメージ、イメージして？
Imagine, just picture it?
That's right Gigi, feel it from the heart!
Feel it!
You can do it!
一人ずつ鳴いてもらうからね？
I'm going to have each of you make the sound, okay?
She's gonna ask each of you to sound out the...
...onomatopoeia that you have come up with.
オッケー？オッケー、オッケー？
Ready? Ready, okay?
全然知らん？
You have no idea?
じゃあ一人ずつ鳴いてもらいますか？
Then should we have everyone make the sound one by one?
じゃ、よぴぴから。よぴぴの馬の鳴き声...
Alright, starting with Yopipi. Yopipi's horse sound...
お願いします。ボイス！
...please. Voice!
「はりきっていこう！」です！
It's "Let's give it our all!"
はりきっていこう？！それ？！それ違くない？！
"Let's give it our all"?! That?! Isn't that wrong?!
I don't think...
そうやって鳴く？！
Does it make that sound?!
馬これしかないですよ！
Horses only do this!
ウマ娘すぎる！
That's way too Uma Musume!
馬これしか知らないですよ、馬！
That's the only horse I know!
じゃあ、続いて、えー、こぼちゃん！
Alright, next up, Kobo-chan!
あー、「ひーほー！ひーほー！」
Ah, "Hee-haw! Hee-haw!"
あー！ひーふー？ひーふー？
Ah! Hee-hoo? Hee-hoo?
ひーふー！
Hee-hoo!
I feel like that's a different sound.
ロバじゃない？！
Isn't that a donkey?!
「ひーひー」？それ別のやつじゃん！
"Hee-hee"? That's a completely different one!
ひーほー、ひーほー！
Hee-haw, hee-haw!
オッケー、オッケー。「ひーふー、ひーふー」ね。
Okay, okay. "Hee-hoo, hee-hoo", right?
じゃあ、続いてジジ！
Alright, next up, Gigi!
えー...
Um...
それ？！
That?!
Wild horse!
リアル！
So realistic!
じゃあ、続いてべーちゃん！
Alright, next up, Bae-chan!
えっと...「うまーーー！」
Um... "UMAAA---!"
めっちゃ日本語しゃべるやん！
It speaks fluent Japanese!
じゃあ、続いて、えー、ラオラ！
Alright, next up, Raora!
Okay, maybe something like...
すごーい！
Amazing!
You're turning into a horse!
リアル！
Realistic!
You're a cat!
めっちゃ似てた！
That was so spot on!
じゃあ...
Alright...
正解は...
The answer is...
馬の鳴き声って何？
What is a horse sound?
「ヒヒーン」でした！
It was "Hihiin"!
ヒヒー？
Hi-hii?
ヒヒーン？
Hihiin?
ヒヒーン！Yes, yes, yes!
Hihiin! Yes, yes, yes!
「ヒヒーン」！そしたらラオラじゃないの？
"Hihiin"! If so, isn't it Raora?
ラオラはリアルすぎたかな？
Was Raora too realistic?
リアルすぎたかな？
Maybe too realistic?
ラオラ？
Raora?
「ヒヒーン」？
ヒヒーン、うん。
"Hihiin"?
Hihiin, yeah.
Oh, there's an "n" at the end!
ヒ・ヒ・ー・ン。
ヒヒーン。
Hi-hi-i-n.
Hihiin.
Why do horses make that sound?!
Sounds like Michael Jackson!
ヒヒーン！
Hihiin!
ヒヒー！
Hee-hee!
Kobo has "hihu" too.
Kobo wrote "hihu" too.
Does it... am I count?
Does it... do I count?
Oh yeah, Kobo does.
Ah, hihu. I have "hihu" too.
No, no hihu?
No, "hihu" no.
No, no "hihu".
フーの？
A "hoo"?
Oh, so it's not counting.
Oh, so it doesn't count.
No count? No count, sorry.
No count? It doesn't count, sorry.
ヒフヒフ。かわいいけどね。
"Hihu hihu." It's cute though.
はい、残念ながら不正解でございます。
Unfortunately, that is incorrect.
あらま。
Oh dear.
では続いて、今から言う言葉の意味を当ててください。
Moving on, please guess the meaning of the phrase I say next.
じゃあ、いきます。
Here we go.
What is the meaning of this?
「ぺこぺこだー！」
"Pekopeko da!"
の意味は？
What does that mean?
あー、はいはいはいはい。
Ah, okay, okay, okay.
What does "peko peko" mean?
ぺこぺこ...
Pekopeko...
お、みんなスラスラと書いてくれている。
Oh, everyone is writing it down smoothly.
ぺこぺこ、ぺこ...
Pekopeko, peko...
ぺこぺこだ！ぺこぺこだー！
"Pekopeko da!" "Pekopeko daa!"
ぺこぺこだー。
"Pekopeko daa."
OKかな？OKかなー？
Are you ready? All done?
かわいいイラストが描かれている。
Some cute illustrations have been drawn.
じゃあ聞いていきますか。
Shall we check the answers?
じゃ、よぴっぴ！
First, Yopippi!
はい！
Yes!
Hungryです！食べたいです！プリン食べたいです！
It means "hungry"! I want to eat! I want to eat pudding!
プリン食べたい！Hungry。
Wants to eat pudding! Hungry.
食べたいです！ぺこぺこです！
I want to eat! Pekopeko!
ぺこぺこ。じゃあ、こぼちゃん！
"Pekopeko". Alright, Kobo-chan!
はい！ぺこぺこ、インドネシア語意味は「laper」です！
Yes! In Indonesian, "pekopeko" means "laper"!
「laper」はどういう意味ですか？よぴっぴ。
What does "laper" mean, Yopippi?
What does that mean?
「laper」は「hungry」！
"Laper" is "hungry"!
あ、hungry！あー！
Ah, hungry! Ahh!
Hungryね。OK。
Hungry, got it. OK.
じゃあ、ジジ！
Next, Gigi!
ジジ、顔だけしか描いてない？
Gigi, did you only draw a face?
じゃ、お腹すいた！ぺこぺこー！
Well, "I'm hungry! Pekopeko!"
あー、お腹空いたね。OK。
Ah, "I'm hungry". OK.
お腹すいた！
I'm hungry!
かわいい。
Cute.
じゃ続いて、べーちゃん！
Next up, Bae-chan!
はい！Hungryです！あれ、腹減った、OK？
Yes! Hungry! Wait, is "hara hetta" (starving) OK?
腹減った、OK！
"Hara hetta" is OK!
じゃあ、ラオラ！
Next, Raora!
あ、Very hungry！
Ah, very hungry!
あー、じゃあ全員同じだね！全員hungry！
Ah, so everyone's the same! Everyone said hungry!
かわいい。
Cute.
えーということで...
And with that...
全員正解ーー！
Everyone is correct!
イエーイ！やったー！
Yay! We did it!
Easy easy! 上手上手！
Easy, easy! Well done, well done!
はい、じゃ続いての意味を当ててくださいね。
Alright, please guess the meaning of the next one too.
Oh, next one is also guess the meaning?
Oh, the next one is also guess the meaning?
はい。じゃあ行きます。
Yes. Here we go.
「チンしてね！」
"Chin shite ne!"
は？Oh!
Huh? Oh!
もう一回？
One more time?
「チンしてね！」
"Chin shite ne!"
チンしてね？チンしてね！
"Chin shite ne?" "Chin shite ne!"
何だろ？チンしてね...
What is it? "Chin shite ne"...
チンしてね！チンしてね...
"Chin shite ne!" "Chin shite ne"...
かわいい、かわいい。
Cute, so cute.
チンしてね...？
"Chin shite ne"...?
チンしてね？
"Chin shite ne"?
チンしてね！
"Chin shite ne!"
分かるかな？声に出したら分かるかもよ。チン...
Do you know? If you say it out loud, you might get it. "Chin"...
チンって何だっけ？
What was "chin" again?
かわいい。
Cute.
これ、これじゃないの？
Is it... is it not this?
OKかな？
Are you ready?
ちょっと下に...
A little lower...
はい、じゃあ聞きますか。
Alright, shall we ask?
よぴっぴ、どうでしょう？
Yopippi, what do you think?
はい！最初はドアのベルだったんだけど、
Yes! At first I thought of a doorbell,
あれピンポンだから、チンしたらマイクロウェーブ？
but that's "ding-dong", so "chin" must mean microwave?
あー、マイクロウェーブ！温める...
Ah, microwave! Warming up...
電子レンジ終わったら「チン」って鳴るじゃない？
When the microwave finishes, it goes "ding", right?
なるほど！はいはいはい。
I see! Okay okay okay.
じゃあ、こぼちゃんは？あれ？あれ？
Now then, Kobo-chan? Huh? Huh?
こぼちゃん！これ、こぼちゃん！
Kobo-chan! Look at this, Kobo-chan!
なんか、チンは、ちょっと...
Like, "chin" is, well...
いやいやいや！危ない危ない！Dangerous!
No no no! That's dangerous! Dangerous!
こぼちゃん！そのものみたい！
Kobo-chan! It sounds like the real thing!
そのチンは...あらー...
That "chin" is... Oh my...
チン please？
"Chin please?"
チン pleaseってトイレ？
"Chin please"... as in the bathroom?!
多分...
Maybe...
わかんない！
I don't know!
なるほど。じゃあ次行きますか。ジジ、ジジ、ジジ。
I see. Well, shall we go to the next one? Gigi, Gigi, Gigi.
わからない...
I don't know...
チンやばい。
Chin is bad.
チンやばい？
Chin is bad?
やばい。チンやばい。
It's bad. Chin is bad.
No やばい！
No, it's not bad!
やばくない、もう！
It's not bad at all, jeez!
じゃ、ベエちゃん、ベエちゃんお願いします。
Then Bae-chan, Bae-chan, please go ahead.
はい。レンジのチンですね。
Yes. It's the "ding" from a microwave.
「温めて」っていうことで...
Meaning "warm it up"...
Please go warm it up in the microwave.
うん、はいはいはい。
Yeah, right, right, right.
じゃあ最後、ラオラ！
And lastly, Raora!
えー、わからない。わからない！
Umm, I don't know. I don't know!
わかんない？ / I don't know.
You don't know? / I don't know.
どうした？
What happened?
Maybe... / Maybe?
Maybe something like... uh...
Maybe when... when the glass, when it touched the glass?
ガラス？
Glasses?
ガラス... 乾杯？
Glasses... a toast?
「チン」って言うかも。
They might say "chin."
確かに！はいはいはい。
That's true! Right, right, right.
Not やばい。
Not yabai.
そう、No やばいね！
Right, "No yabai", exactly!
No やばい。 / Not やばい。
No yabai. / Not yabai.
Not やばい！
Not yabai!
もう、分かんないよ！
Geez, you have no idea!
じゃあ、こちらはですね、正解は...
Well then, for this one, the correct answer is...
マイクロウェーブ！チン！
Microwave! Chin!
マイクロウェーブ。はい、ご飯を温めてください...
Microwave. Yes, "Please warm up the food"...
...っていう。
...is what it means.
あー、電子レンジで！
Ah, in the microwave!
そっかー。
I see.
If you want to warm up food in a microwave, you'd be like, "Chin shite ne."
「チンしてね」。あー、なるほど。
"Chin shite ne." Ah, I see.
例えばご飯をこう置いといて...
For example, leaving the meal out...
後に帰ってきた人、ご飯が冷めちゃってるから...
for someone coming home later, since the meal has gotten cold...
「チンしてね」ってメモを残したりしますね。
you might leave a note saying, "Chin shite ne."
おー！なるほど！
Ooh! I see!
なるほどー。
I see.
こぼ、「こぼチンしてね」？
Kobo, like "Kobo, chin shite ne"?
Yeah, like, "Please warm it up for me. Chin shite ne."
Oh, okay. So if you wanna say "pee, please"?
Yeah, how do you say that? I might need that one.
No pee!
No, no pee!
じゃ、じゃあ pee はどう言ったらいいの？
Then, how should I say "pee"?
Pee って何？ / Pee please!
What is "pee"? / Pee please!
オノマトペは pee please...
The onomatopoeia is pee please...
Pee って何？
What's "pee"?
Pee ってさ、おしっこ？
Wait, is "pee" pee?
おしっこ？ / おしっこ。
Pee? / Pee.
あ、じゃあ「しー」とかですね。「しー」。「シャー」とか。
Ah, then it's like "shii". "Shii". Or "shaa".
シャー。
Shaa.
シャープリーズ？
Shaa please?
シャープリーズ！シャープリーズ！
Shaa please! Shaa please!
シャー、なるほど。
Shaa, I see.
はい。「シャーして」とか。
Yes, like "Shaa shite."
シャーお願い！
Shaa please!
No, no, no, no! No, だめね！だめだめよ！
No, no, no, no! No, no good! Definitely not!
すみません、シャーお願い！
Excuse me, shaa please!
だめだめだめ！だめー！
No no no! Nooo!
変な日本語教えないで！
Don't teach her weird Japanese!
ありがとうございます、分かりました！
Thank you very much, understood!
やべえ...
Oh man...
えー、じゃあ、ネクスト行きましょう！こちらでございます。
Well then, let's go to the next one! Here it is.
え、「静まり返ったとき」。めっちゃ静かなとき使う...
Uh, "When it falls dead silent." The one used when it's super quiet...
...オノマトペは何でしょうか？
...what would that onomatopoeia be?
What's the onomatopoeia that they use when it goes really quiet?
Oh, maybe I remember...
え？
Eh?
あ、何だっけ？静かなとき...
Ah, what was it? When it's quiet...
What that mean?
What? Really, really quiet... / What that mean?
静かなときも音があるんですよ。
There's a sound even when it's quiet.
Like when it goes really quiet all of a sudden, what's the onomatopoeia that they would use?
You can write it in romaji, or you can just sound it out.
I'm gonna write the... the onomatopoeia I just learned!
漫画読んだら分かるかもね。漫画に書いてあることもあるかも。
If you read manga, you might know it. It might be written in manga.
ジャパニーズ漫画。
Japanese manga.
Might be in manga that you've read before... / What is it?
Like that? Is that how you spell it?
I don't know if it's valid.
まあ、まあいいでしょう！
Well, well, it's fine!
何何何何？
What, what, what, what?
いやいやいや。
No, no, no.
じゃあ聞いていきますね。よぴぴから。
Alright, let's hear them. Starting from Yopipi.
はい。「しーん」。
Yes. "Shiin."
です。 / 「しーん」ね。 / 多分。
That's it. / "Shiin", right. / Probably.
ここやって「しーん」。あー。
Doing this, "shiin." Ahh.
はいはいはい。じゃあ続いてこぼちゃん！
Right, right, right. Next up, Kobo-chan!
しー。
Shii.
うんうんうん。「しー」。 / しー。
Mhm mhm mhm. "Shii." / Shii.
「しー」。はいはい。
"Shii." Right, right.
じゃあ、ジジ！
Then, Gigi!
しゃあ！
Shaa!
しゃあ？！
Shaa?!
しゃあ！ / しゃあ？！
Shaa! / Shaa?!
まあまあまあ...
Well, well, well...
Isn't that the pee?
No!
Well, wouldn't it get quiet after you pee?
Quiet after you pee?
Oh...
じゃ、続いてアーニャちゃん。
Next up, Anya-chan.
いやー、忘れた。なんか…「すん」
Ah, I forgot. Like... "sun"?
ああ、「すん」。
Ah, "sun".
違う、「すん」はちょっと違うか。
No, "sun" is a bit off, isn't it?
「しーん」だったか。
Was it "shiin"?
いや、どっちかと思ってたんだよね。
Yeah, I was wondering which one it was.
なるほど、なるほど。
I see, I see.
うんうん。
Yeah, yeah.
うーん...
Hmm...
お、ジジ？
Oh, Gigi?
Mhm, yeah.
Yeah, I think it's "shiin".
あ、「しーん」。
Ah, "shiin".
Like, I remember when I read some mangas,
Like, I remember when I read some manga,
but I might be wrong.
Maybe it's "shiin".
うんうんうん。
Right, right.
Shiin. Okay, okay.
漫画ね。Got it, got it. Okay.
From manga, right. Got it, got it. Okay.
じゃ、正解行きましょう。
Well then, let's see the answer.
正解は、「しーん」でございます！
The correct answer is... "shiin"!
やっぱりー！
I knew it!
Shiit!
ということで、ラオラが正解だね！
Which means Raora got it right!
Yeah! You're so close Gigi, you're so close!
Yeah! You were so close, Gigi, so close!
Yeah, I was close! Gigi was close!
ジジのは、「しー」
Gigi wrote "shii".
そう、「しー」。
Right, "shii".
「ん」が必要ですね、こぼちゃん。「し・い・ん」。
You needed the "n", Kobo-chan. "Shi-i-n".
ねー。
Yeah.
そうですねー。
That's right.
Nice try!
惜しい！惜しかったー。
So close! That was so close!
Very close. まあまあまあ、はいはいはい。
Very close. Well, well, okay, okay.
Close enough.
ジジは絶対違うからね。
Gigi's was definitely wrong, though.
「しゃー」は…
As for "shaa"...
そっちじゃないですか？おしっこじゃなくて。
Isn't it for that? A shower, not peeing.
そう、さっきのピーの音…
Yeah, the earlier pee sound...
一応なんか理屈的にも間違ってないと思うすけどね。
I feel like logically it's not wrong, though.
え？
Eh?
ほら、ジジがさ、立っておしっこした後にさ、静かになるじゃん。
Look, when Gigi stands and pees, it gets quiet afterwards, right?
あ、そうそう。
Ah, right, right.
だから「しゃー」。
That's why "shaa".
「しゃー」
"Shaa".
ちょっと違うかなー。
That's a bit different, though.
I was... I was explaining your logic!
Oh, okay! Thank you. So you're defending me.
Yeah, I was defending you.
はい、じゃあ…
Alright, well...
I got you, I got you.
続いていきましょう。
Let's move on to the next one.
続いて…
Next...
とっても冷たい飲み物を
What is the onomatopoeia
表すオノマトペは何でしょうか？
used to describe an extremely cold drink?
Oh, what's the sound of an extremely cold drink?
飲み物？そう、冷たい…
A drink? Yes, cold...
えー？
Eh?
あ、あれとあれだけど…
Ah, it's either this or that, but...
「何々に冷えた」って言いますね。
People say "chilled to [blank]".
あれでしょう。
It's that one, right?
Cold drink?
I only have one word in my head again!
Do I write it again?!
Cold drink.
これもね、漫画に出てくるかもね。
This one might also appear in manga.
Every manga... Uh-huh, uh-huh.
分からない！
I don't know!
イメージ！イメージ！
Just imagine it!
Image or sound? If I get it wrong, will you buy...
What do you have in mind?
Just do it! Just do it!
I'm scared!
No, it's okay!
Nooo...
ジジがなんかヤバそうなやつを考え… そうなんです。
Gigi is thinking of something dangerous... Indeed.
な、何を書こうとしてるのジジ？大丈夫？
Wh-What are you trying to write, Gigi? You okay?
大丈夫。
I'm okay.
Gigi大丈夫？大丈夫ね？
Gigi, are you okay? You're okay, right?
大丈夫、大丈夫。
You're fine, you're fine.
I'm fine, I'm fine.
大丈夫、はいはい。
You're fine, okay.
でもあれかな、ビールとかに結構言うかな？
It's often used for things like beer, though.
Oh, use it with beer?
うん。
Yeah.
オッケー？
Ready?
じゃあ、行きますか。
Well then, shall we see?
えー、じゃあよぴぴ！
Uh, first up, Yopipi!
はい！
Yes!
確か「キンキン」なんとかのほにゃららです。はい。
If I recall, it's "kin-kin" something or other. Yes.
えっと、なんか、あの、この前スタジオで誰かさん…
Um, recently at the studio, someone...
ホロメンが誰かさんが、あのマネージャーに「キンキンの飲み物欲しいです」って言われた。
...one of the Holomem told their manager, "I want an ice-cold drink!"
おおー！なるほどー！
Ooh! I see!
そうそうそう。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
スタジオで、あの夏ぐらいで、うん、
At the studio around summertime, yeah,
誰かさんちょっと忘れちゃったんだけど、スタジオでなんか聞いたことがある。
I forgot who it was, but I remember hearing it at the studio.
あー、「キンキン」ね！
Ah, "kin-kin"! Okay!
オッケー！はい、じゃあこぼ！
Okay! Next, Kobo!
Uh, so I thought like...
when you... after you drink cold, a really cold drink,
うん。
Uh-huh.
your... uh... after that, your head will hurt and then you will say "atata".
ああー！
Ahhh!
なんか、冷たいもの飲んだあとさ、頭痛くなるんじゃないですか？
Like, your head hurts after drinking something cold, right?
あー、なるほど！
Ah, I see!
そのときに「あたたたた」
And at that time, "ow-ow-ow-ow"!
なるほどね！はいはい。
I see, I see! Okay.
だからこそ「あたたた」って答えました。
That's why she answered "atatata".
「あたた」ね。オッケー、オッケー。
"Atata", right. Okay, okay.
Uh-huh.
はいはい。じゃあ続いて、ジジ！
Right. Next up, Gigi!
Mmm... eh...
お？お？
Oh? Oh?
「寒い」
"Cold".
「寒い」？！
"Cold"?!
寒いねー！寒い！
Cold indeed! Cold!
Yes!
寒い？
Cold?
「寒い、うまい！」
"Cold, delicious!"
「寒い、うまい」？！
"Cold, delicious"?!
かわいい。
Cute.
オッケー？
Okay?
寒い。寒い飲み物、オッケー？
Cold. Cold drink, okay?
Error processing subtitles for this segment.
オッケー？
Okay?
いけるかな？
Ready?
じゃあ聞いてこ。
Then let's ask around.
じゃあヨピピから。
Let's start with Yopipi.
はーい。えっと、きらーんかのそのキラキラとかのそういうのー...
Okay. Um, like "kiraan" or "kirakira", things like that...
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
かなと思ってて。でも今思ってたらあれだなと思ってて。
I thought it was that, but thinking about it now, maybe not.
おっ、変えますか？
Oh, do you want to change it?
あ、いや、大丈夫です！
Ah, no, it's fine!
なんか、そう、なんか...
Like, yeah, kind of...
そのキラキラもっと強いのがなんかいつも太陽...
A stronger version of "kirakira", like usually the sun...
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
太陽になんか...あ、太陽「ピーッ」ってなっちゃうじゃないですか。
for the sun... Ah, if I say it, it'll get bleeped out, right?
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
太陽によく使われるものかな？
Something that's often used for the sun?
なるほど。はい、はい、はい、はい。
I see. Yes, yes, yes, yes.
じゃあ、こぼちゃん！
Next, Kobo-chan!
可愛いですか？
Is it cute?
Cuz I heard someone saying...
uh...
Pokemon?
Aha, aha.
So, I think like...
ピカピカ！
Pika-pika!
めっちゃ可愛い！
That's so cute!
Oy!
Pika-pika, right?
オッケー。
Okay.
確かに強い。確かに強い、ピカピカ。
It's definitely strong. Definitely strong, "pika-pika".
確かに、ピカピカ強い。
Indeed, pika-pika is strong.
Strong, strong pika-pika.
じゃあ続いてジジ！
Okay, next is Gigi!
Hehehe.
GG muri.
GG impossible.
キラキラ？
Sparkling?
Yeah...
ぎーらぎーらー！
Gira-gira!
はいはいはい！ギラギラ。オッケー！
Yes, yes, yes! Gira-gira. Okay!
オッケーオッケー。じゃあCC行きましょう！
Okay, okay. Let's go with CC!
あ、僕もピカピカだと思った。
Ah, I thought it was "pika-pika" too.
はい、ピカピカね！
Yes, pika-pika!
オッケー。
Okay.
うん、えーじゃあ、ラオラ！
Yeah. Um, next, Raora!
Ah, ah, same for me. I heard about Pokemon...
Oh my god.
...so I thought about pika-pika too.
こぼが言ったからね。
Because Kobo said it, right?
はい。
Yes.
なるほど、なるほど。
I see, I see.
オッケー。じゃあ正解いきましょう！
Okay. Then let's check the correct answer!
正解は...
The answer is...
ギラギラ！で、ジジ正解！
"Gira-gira"! So Gigi is correct!
Yay!
ギラギラ！
Gira-gira!
ギラギラ、bitch!
Gira-gira, bitch!
天才じゃん！
You're a genius!
天才！ジジ天才！
Genius! Gigi is a genius!
買収されたわ。買収されたわ。
I was bribed. I was bribed.
Wait, what?
ピカピカちょっと惜しくて、
"Pika-pika" was pretty close,
それがね、ビカビカとかだったら正解。
but if it were "bika-bika", that would've been right.
ああ、ビカビカ？
Ah, bika-bika?
もっと「び」「び」のが眩しいね。
With "bi" "bi", it feels more dazzling.
あ、ビカビカの方が強いんだ。
Ah, bika-bika is stronger.
そう。ピカピカはまあキラキラと同じくらいかな。
Right. Pika-pika is about the same as kira-kira.
同じ？
The same?
えーーー！
Ehhh?!
なるほど。ちょっと弱いかな。ビカビカ、ギラギラ。
I see. It's a bit weaker. Bika-bika, gira-gira...
So pika-pika is on the same level as kira-kira.
うん。
Yeah.
でもなんか、いつも聞いてるのがなんか「ギラギラ太陽なんとか」っていう...
But I feel like I'm always hearing things like "gira-gira sun something"...
あ、そうそうそうそう！
Ah, right, right, right, right!
あ、そう？
Oh, really?
濡れ頭巾のね、あのギラファもね。
From Nurezukin, the "Girafar" too...
あー、ギラギラ...ファンミーティング、ギラファ。
Ah, Gira-gira... Fan meeting, Girafar.
とかもね、同じ感じで「明るい、眩しい」みたいな感じだと思いますね。
Things like that too. In the same way, I think it's like "bright, dazzling".
なるほど。面白い。
I see. That's interesting.
I see, I see, I see. Now you know.
Bribing works?
Bribing works? I mean, I could bribe her. Bribing works!
Yeah, if that works.
Okay, nice, nice, nice. Nice info.
さあ、続いていきましょう！続いて、
Now then, let's move on! Next,
同じ感じでございますけども、
it's the same kind of question,
心臓のこの音、「どきどき」
this sound of the heart: "doki-doki"...
をもっと強く！
Make it stronger!
Stronger doki-doki.
Doki-doki.
表現すると？
...how would you express it?
Bigger than doki-doki.
ドキ？ あれ？
Doki? Huh?
これもね、何パターンかあるから、
This one has several variations too,
合ってたら大丈夫です。
so if you match any of them, it's fine.
何パターンかあるんだ。
There are several variations.
どちらでもいいって感じですか、そしたら？
Then any of them is good, in that case?
うん、まあ2つ、3つくらい表現はあるかな。
Yeah, there are about two or three expressions.
Yeah...
なんかな...
I wonder...
ドキドキ...
Doki-doki...
うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah.
うーん、ドキドキね。
Hmm, doki-doki.
Doki doki doki doki.
ドキ？
Doki?
ドキドキ...
Doki-doki...
ドキッをもっと強く、強く。
Make "doki" stronger, stronger.
強く？
Stronger?
うん。
Yeah.
ドキドキが...
Doki-doki is...
ちなみに弱くすると...
By the way, if you make it weaker...
うーん、まあ弱くすると、
Hmm, well if you make it weaker,
「とくん、とくん」とかですね。
it's like "tokun, tokun".
ああ...おっ、オッケー。
Ah... Oh, okay.
これもちょっとヒントになるかな？
Maybe this will be a bit of a hint too?
とくん、とくん...どき、どき...
Tokun, tokun... doki, doki...
Next. Another like similar level is tokun tokun, so that's a hint.
So you want something stronger than tokun tokun.
Oh...
All right.
あ、これもちょっと何か可愛い声でまつり先輩、あ、まつりお姉さんって言ったらもっとヒントくれます？
Ah, for this too, if I call you Matsuri-senpai—ah, Matsuri-oneesan in a cute voice, will you give us more hints?
ヒント？！
Hints?!
ヒントかー。
Hints, huh.
もっとヒントくれます？
Will you give us more hints?
か、可愛くまつりお姉さんって言ったら、ヒントもっとくれます？
If I say "Matsuri-oneesan" cutely, will you give more hints?
あー、オッケーオッケー。
Ah, okay, okay.
いいよ。どうぞ！
Sure. Go ahead!
え？ え、い、いいんですか？
Eh? I-Is it okay?
いいよ。
Sure.
え、いいんですか？
Eh, really okay?
うん。
Yeah.
まつりお姉...
Matsuri-onee...
ねえちゃん ちょっとあの ヒントお願いします
Big sis, could you give us a hint, please?
しょうがないにゃあ
Well, I guess I have no choice, meow.
ひとつだけでいいから おねえちゃん
Just one is fine, big sis!
ひとつだけ
Just one!
Oh my god!
めっちゃこれヒントだけどー
This is a huge hint, but...
あー まあ 強調するのに
well, to emphasize something,
日本では結構 小っちゃい「っ」を入れたりとか
in Japanese, we often insert a small "tsu" and such...
あ！ あ！
Ah! Ah!
あとはー
Also...
ドロドロです！
It's dorodoro!
そうですね。あと言葉を変えるんだったら、あのー
Right. And if you change the word itself, um...
なんだろ、なんだろうな
what is it... what would it be...
大きな、大きな音っぽいというか
like a bigger, louder sound, or...
まあ、どれもね、大きそうだけどね
well, all of them seem loud, though.
はい、そんな感じですかね。
Yeah, something like that.
はい！ ありがとう、ねえちゃん！
Yes! Thank you, big sis!
うお！
Whoa!
よし！
Alright!
Okay, okay, okay.
You could totally bribe the MC.
Okay!
じゃあ、聞いちゃいますよ。
All right, I'm gonna ask you all.
Why did you have to bribe the MC?
Whatever it takes to win!
じゃあ、えー、よーぴーって行きますか？
Well then, uh, shall we go with Yopi?
はい！「ドックン」です！
Yes! Mine is "dokkun"!
はい、「ドックン」。
Yes, "dokkun".
ドックン、ドックン... ドックンドックン
Dokkun, dokkun... Dokkun dokkun.
ほうー。
Ooh.
えー、じゃあ、こぼ。
Uh, next, Kobo.
Uh, I I remember to mock Zeta about...
Uh, I remembered mocking Zeta about...
...a part of her original song lyrics. It's...
"babu babu", but it's actually "baku baku" or...
Mm, baku baku...
バクバク
Baku baku.
Yeah, something like that.
あー、バクバク。ほうほうほう、うんうんうん。
Ah, baku baku. I see, I see, mm-hm.
じゃあ、続いてジージ。
Then next, Gigi.
はい！ ウマ娘！
Yes! Uma Musume!
どっきどき どきゅん！ どきゅん！
Doki doki, dokyun! Dokyun!
あー、ドッキュン！ ドッキュンもある！ あー！
Ah, dokyun! Dokyun is one too! Ahhh!
はい！
Yes!
はいはいはい、なるほど。確かに。
Yes, yes, yes, I see. Indeed.
じゃあ、べーちゃん。
Then, Bae-chan.
いやもう、どきどきをもっと強くして、もはや心臓破裂...
Well, making "doki-doki" even stronger, like a heart burst...
ドドドドドド！
DODODODODO!
Another heart attack.
踏破音「ドドドドド」になっちゃう。
It becomes a stomping sound, "dododododo."
はい。じゃあ、ラオラ。
Yes. Then, Raora.
It's a "Bakkun bakkun"!
It's "bakkun bakkun"!
あー、ばっくんばっくん！
Ah, bakkun bakkun!
ばっくんばっくん！ ばっくんばっくん！
Bakkun bakkun! Bakkun bakkun!
I was listening recently, so...
おー、へえー。
Oh, really?
なるほど、なるほど。
I see, I see.
Must be it.
これ、結構みんな違うんだけどー
Now, everyone has something different here, but...
正解はー
the correct answer is...
ん？
Hm?
これね、全員正解でいいかなと思います！
I think everyone can be considered correct for this!
Oh, everyone's right!
Everyone's right.
We're all winners!
結構いろんな表現があってー
There are actually a lot of different expressions...
へえー。
Hoo...
まあ、「ドッキン」とか「ドックンドックン」とか。
Well, like "dokkin" or "dokkun dokkun."
うん、「どきどき」...「どっきどき」とか。
Yeah, "doki-doki"... "dokkidoki" and so on.
ドキドキね。
Dokidoki, yeah.
ドドドドも強そう。
Dodododo seems intense too.
ドドドド。
Dodododo.
ドドドドはもう死んでるよ。
With dodododo, you're already dead.
死んでる？
Dead?!
瀕死そう。
Sounds on the verge of death.
緊張、緊張してるときとかに「ドドドドド」っていう表現もあったりとか。
Like when you're super nervous, people sometimes express it as "dododododo" too.
はい。
Yes.
ということで全員正解。素晴らしい！
So, everyone's correct. Wonderful!
イエーイ！ やったー！
Yay! We did it!
じゃあ、ちょっと...
Now then, a little...
みんな上手！
Everyone is so good!
そう、上手！
Yes, so good!
今度は今から、とあるサウンドを聞いてもらいます。
Next, you will listen to a certain sound.
あの、チャンネルにね、ボイスを貼りますので。
I'll post an audio clip in the channel.
これ、何て言っているんでしょうかという問題でございますね。
The question is: what is it saying?
何て言っている？
What is it saying?
いや、何と...何と聞こえるか。
Well, what... what does it sound like?
今からセミの鳴き声を送ります。
I'm now going to send the sound of a cicada chirping.
うん。何と言っているでしょうか、セミは。
Yup. What is the cicada saying?
All right. They've sent, uh, she's sent a little voice clip. What is this cicada saying...
...in the voice clip?
オッケー？
Okay?
じゃあ、リスナーさんにも聞かせます。こちらです。
Then I'll let the listeners hear it as well. Here it is.
Oh, so we have to come up with the onomatopoeia. なるほどね。
Oh, so we have to come up with an onomatopoeia. I see.
From listening to it?
Is it—is there on the...
It's in the chat, in...
はい、これは何と鳴いて...
Yes, what does this sound...
なるほど、なるほど。
I see, I see.
はーはーはーはー。
Aha, aha.
So what is that sound that the cicada is making?
日本人だったらね、絶対にわかるね。
If you're Japanese, you'd definitely know this.
Ch-ch-ch-ch- How do you draw "chi-chi"? Chi-ch-
Cicada? How do you pronounce it?
Cicada.
Cicada?
Cicada. Cicada.
Cicada.
It's cicada.
It's cicada? I always pronounced it "chicada".
"Chicada"!
Enchilada.
I don't know how to pronounce it!
I thought it was "chicada".
これは何かー。
What could it be...
What does it look like? Chi-cicadas?
Cicadas.
Cicada.
おー、わかるかな？
Ooh, will they get it?
It has big wings.
Yeah.
よし、
All right,
You sure? I've never seen it before.
I see it all the time inside here.
セミ
Cicadas.
Really?
They're like everywhere.
They fall and they cannot fly again.
They die quickly.
これ分かったら
If you know this one,
JPやね。
you're definitely Japanese.
さすがに。
For sure.
セミ
Cicada.
本物のセミ見たことないんですか？
You've never seen a real cicada before?
え？
Huh?
え？いないの？
Eh? Are there none where you live?
いや、いるとは思うんだけど、
No, I think they're there, but...
声は聞こえるけど
even though I can hear their voices,
姿が... なんかどこにいるのか分かんない。
I don't know what they look like or where they are.
そうなんだ！
Is that so!
え、子供の頃セミ獲りとかしないの？
Like, didn't you catch cicadas as a kid?
ない。
Never.
ああー...
Ah...
あれは多分、結構なんか日本文化的な...
That's probably pretty much a Japanese culture thing...
へー！そうなんだ！
Wow! Is that so!
ないない。
Never did that.
じゃあセミの種類とか言われても、あんま分かんないのか。
So even if someone mentions cicada species, you wouldn't really know them?
分かんない！全員セミだもん！
No idea! To me, they're all just cicadas!
確かに！全員セミだもん！
True! They're all just cicadas!
へえーー！そうなんだ。
Heeey! I see.
You guys You guys Any one of you guys caught cicadas before?
You guys, any one of you guys caught cicadas before?
Cicadas Bae, cicada, cicada... Ever caught one before?
No.
But I got...
I got one in my balcony.
Is it big?
え？
Huh?
On your balcony?
Yeah! And it was huge!
バルコニー？
Balcony?
It was like super big!
I would cry if I was you.
I would cry if I were you.
And it was super loud!
ば、バルコニー？
B-Balcony?
ベランダベランダ。
Veranda, veranda.
ベランダね。
Veranda, right.
ベランダにいた？
It was on your veranda?
へえー！そんなに大きいの？セミって。
Wow! Are cicadas really that big?
結構でかいよ。
They're pretty huge.
よくいるよ、その辺に死んでるやつとか。
You see them around a lot, like dead ones lying around.
マジ？
Really?
Big bug.
こぼは大丈夫かな？
Is Kobo doing okay?
大丈夫くない！
Not okay!
え、大丈夫くない？何回も聴いていいよ。
Eh, not okay? You can listen to it again!
大丈夫じゃない！何回も。
Not okay! Over and over.
大丈夫じゃない。
Not okay.
Can I have hint?
Can I have a hint?
ヒントお願い。
A hint, please.
ヒント？
A hint?
ヒントはー
The hint is...
なんかあの、「ショワショワショワ」って言ってるのは無視していい。
You can ignore the part that goes "shwa shwa shwa."
その大きい低めの音
That loud, lower-pitched sound...
のセミさんは何て言ってるかだねー。
What is that cicada saying?
おおー
Ooh.
Focus on the lower sounding notes, ignore the "shwa-shwa-shwa-shwa" in the background.
困ってるねー。
They're struggling, huh?
オッケー。
Okay.
オッケー？
Okay?
じゃあ行きましょう。よぴぴから。
Then let's go. Starting with Yopipi!
はい、えっ、みーみん。
Yes, um, "Mii-min".
はいはいはい。みーみん。
Yes, yes, yes. "Mii-min".
はい、みーみんね、オッケー！
All right, "Mii-min," got it!
じゃあこぼちゃん！
Next, Kobo-chan!
ちー！ちー！
Chii! Chii!
かわいい！
Cute!
ちー！
Chii!
ちー、ちー？
Chii, chii?
ちー？ちー？ちー？オッケーオッケー。
Chii? Chii? Chii? Okay, okay.
ちー、ちーだね。
"Chii, chii," right?
かわいい！
Cute!
はい！じゃあジジ！
Okay! Next, Gigi!
Gigiは、「ジー、ジージー」
Gigi is: "Jii, jii-jii."
ジージー？
Jii-jii?
ジジの鳴き声？
Gigi's own call?
Gigi's call?
おー
Oh.
じゃあ続いてベッちゃん！
Next up, Bae-chan!
えー、「ウィーーー！」
Um, "Wiiiii!"
「ウィーーー！」
"Wiiiii!"
オッケーオッケー！
Okay, okay!
じゃあ、ラスト、ラオラ！
Then last, Raora!
あ、It's, "kri kri kri"
Ah, it's "kri kri kri"
かわいい！くりくり！
Cute! "Kuri-kuri"!
kri kri
オッケーオッケー！
Okay, okay!
じゃあ、正解行きましょう！正解は！
Now, let's reveal the correct answer! The answer is...
はい！
Yes!
「みーんみんみんみん」で、
"Miiin min min min", so...
おーー！
Ohhh!
よぴぴ正解でーす！
Yopipi is correct!
やったーー！
Yay!
Yeah!
Damn, "min"! It doesn't sound like "min" at all!
How is that Japanese?!
なんか聞こえないんだよね、「M」。
You really can't hear the "M".
「M」の音なくない？
Isn't the "M" sound missing?
There's no "M" sound!
このセミの名前がそもそも「ミンミンゼミ」という名前のセミで、
The name of this cicada to begin with is "Minminzemi,"
ああああー！
Aaaah!
ミンミンゼミね。
Minminzemi, I see.
へーー！
Ohhh!
「みーんみんみんみん」て、日本人には聞こえてますね。
so to Japanese people, it sounds like "miiin min min min."
そうなんだ。はい。
I see. Got it.
へええー
Huhhh.
じゃあ続いて、ネクストセミ行きますよ！
All right, moving on, here comes the next cicada!
ネクストセミ？
Next cicada?
Another cicada sound?
Nice voice!
There's more?!
Let's go!
ワンモアセミ、行きます。
One more cicada coming up.
One more cicada, okay.
はい、ワンモアセミ。セミ2、こちらです。
Yes, one more cicada. Cicada 2 is this one.
じゃあ皆さんにも聴かせます。
Let's let everyone listen.
ほいっ
Here!
セミ2
Cicada 2.
あれ？
Huh?
I don't know...
これセミ？
Is this a cicada?
なんだこれ？！
What is this?!
Hmm? Am I suffocating?
何？！
What?!
はいはい、めっちゃ聴こえますね。
Yes, yes, you can hear it so clearly.
多分日本人にはめちゃめちゃ聴こえる。
Japanese people can definitely hear it super clearly.
へえーー
Heeey...
What's the sound from?
え？
Eh?
I don't know!
What the heck?!
セミバージョン2ですよ。
It's cicada version two!
へえー...
Huhhh...
もうわからん！
I have no idea anymore!
分かるかなー？
Can you guess it?
セミ2ね。
Cicada 2, right.
セミ2。
Cicada 2.
ヒントをお願いします！
Please give us a hint!
ヒントー？！
A hint?!
ヒントはー...
The hint is...
Error processing subtitles for this segment.
...セミだったり
...or a cicada.
アブラゼミ
Large brown cicada.
はい / イェー
Yes. / Yeah.
日本人だったら
If you're Japanese,
セミの声を聞くだけで、何のセミか分かります。
just by hearing a cicada's chirp, you can tell which cicada it is.
え！？ Wow!
Huh?! Wow!
Wow!
They can differentiate what kind of
cicada it is depending on what it sounds like?
There's different enchiladas?
Enchila... Yeah, so what we heard were two different enchiladas, Gigi.
So you're saying that there is an enchilada that says "GG"?
Yeah, there is. Yes, there is.
あの熱... え、三種類って何の名前だったっけ？
That heat... Wait, what were the names of the three kinds?
えーと、「ジージージー」はアブラゼミですね。
Well, "zii-zii-zii" is the large brown cicada.
アブラゼミ！ / はい。
Large brown cicada! / Yes.
アブラゼ... / 茶色いやつ。
Aburaze... / The brown one.
アブラゼミ / アブラゼミ...
Aburazemi. / Aburazemi...
アブラゼミ / Yes. / アブラゼミ
Aburazemi. / Yes. / Aburazemi.
はい。 / All together? / Large brown cicada.
Yes. / All together? / Large brown cicada.
Cicada all wet. / はい。
Cicada all wet. / Yes.
Large brown cicada, ghost.
なるほど！
I see!
なるほどー / なるほど！
I see. / I see!
はい、なるほど。
Yes, I see.
続いて、ラスト問題！
Next up, the final question!
Oh, last! Last!
これはめっちゃ、ちょっとジャパニーズすぎる、難しいと思うんですけど...
This one is super... a bit too Japanese, so I think it'll be difficult, but...
え？
Huh?
これ解けたら、もういつ、いつ日本に来ても戦えます。
If you can solve this, you'll be able to hold your own anytime you come to Japan.
戦える？ / 戦える？ Okay. / Okay?
Hold our own? / Hold our own? Okay. / Okay?
日本には独特な、これにしか使わないオノマトペがあります。
In Japan, there are unique onomatopoeia that are only used for one specific thing.
えー... / おお！
And... / Ooh!
桃が川から流れてくるオノマトペは何でしょう？
What is the onomatopoeia for a peach floating down a river?
What is the onomatopoeia for when a peach comes flowing down the river?
Slider peach?
これ桃太郎読んでないんだったら...
If they haven't read Momotaro...
桃太郎読んでねえ！読んでないんだったらできないじゃないですか、これ桃太郎。
You haven't read Momotaro! If you haven't, you can't solve this! It's Momotaro!
これ分かったら、もう日本に来ていただいていつでも...
If you know this, you can come visit Japan anytime...
So what is the sound that a peach makes when it flows down the river?
It's a very, very specific onomatopoeia.
I'm guessing if you know the story of Momotaro...
字が、字が汚いや。ええと...
My handwriting is messy. Um...
Is it folklore?
Yeah, you know the one with the Peach Boy, the Momotaro?
Peach Boy.
Yeah, it's very specific.
わかんない。これ...
I don't know this...
We gotta guess, we gotta guess, we gotta guess.
桃にしか使わないですね。リンゴとかが川に流れてても使わない。
It's only used for peaches. Even if an apple were floating down a river, you wouldn't use it.
えー...
Eeh...
Only used for peaches. It's only peaches.
Oh my god.
No, I'm sure this is gonna be really weird.
これ桃太郎読んでないとわかんないやつ。
You won't know this if you haven't read Momotaro.
桃太郎一回読んだんだよね。
I read Momotaro once, you know.
あ、じゃあわかるじゃん！
Oh, then you should know it!
Maybe I know that legend, but 'cause I've watched...
If you read the actual book, it's written in the actual book, like in Japanese.
So if you haven't read it, then you probably don't know.
そんなこと言われてもー！
Even if you say that...!
なんか確か前に、雑談配信でこれのことちょっと語った気がする。
I think I talked a bit about this in a chatting stream before.
そうなんだ！
Really!
そう。「なんでこうなったの？」って言われたら「分かんない」って...
Yeah. But if they asked "Why did it become that?", I'd say "I don't know..."
え、すごいね、でも。話すんだ。
Wow, that's amazing though. Talking about that.
昔話ね。
The folktale, right?
はい。
Yes.
なんだっけ...
What was it again...
これはね、多分知らないと本当に当てられないと思うけど...
Well, I really don't think you can guess it if you don't already know, but...
日本人だったら、ちっちゃい子からおじいちゃんおばあちゃんまでみんなわかるからね。
If you're Japanese, everyone from little kids to grandparents knows it.
桃の川流れてる音なんだって。
Apparently that's the sound of a peach floating down a river.
おおー。
Ooh.
はい。じゃあ行きましょうか、最終問題。じゃ、れいぴー、どうでしょう？
All right, shall we see? The final question. So, Reipy, what do you have?
はい、どんぶらこです。
Yes, it's "donburako."
はい、どんぶらこ！どんぶらこ、オッケー！
Yes, donburako! Donburako, okay!
じゃ、こぼちゃん！ / はい。
Next, Kobo-chan! / Yes.
おしり？もんごもんご。
Butt? Mongo mongo.
もんごもんご？ / もんごもんごー / もんごもんご。
Mongo mongo? / Mongo mongo~ / Mongo mongo.
可愛い！
Cute!
お尻みたい？流れてるの。
Looks like a butt? Floating along.
うん。お尻みたいね。
Yeah. Looks like a butt, right?
じゃあ、ジジ！
Next, Gigi!
If I saw a huge peach floating in the water...
and it was like a really big peach and it was huge, and you know, like a peach,
I would go, "Ah, wa! でかい！"
I would go, "Ah, wow! It's huge!"
めちゃめちゃジューシー！でかい！
Super juicy! Huge!
ジューシー？ / おばあちゃん...
Juicy? / Grandma...
ジューシー、でかい！
Juicy, huge!
でかいのね。 / そう言うの？「でかっ」ってなっちゃうんだ。
Huge, huh. / Is that what you'd say? You'd just go "It's huge!"
お尻でかい！
Huge butt!
Oh my. / Oh my. / はい。
Oh my. / Oh my. / Yes.
じゃあ、べーちゃん！
Next, Bae-chan!
川が... ドンピシャッ！っていう...
The river goes... "Donpisha!" like that...
ドンピシャッ？
Donpisha?
水ね。水の音がドンピシャッね。
The water, right. The sound of water goes donpisha.
ドンピシャッ。 / はい。 / ドンピシャッ。
Donpisha. / Yes. / Donpisha.
続いてラオラ！
Next up, Raora!
Maybe it's ぷかぷか？
Maybe it's puka-puka?
あ、ぷかぷか！
Ah, puka-puka!
ぷかぷか。 / ぷかぷか、可愛い。
Puka-puka. / Puka-puka, that's cute.
ぷかぷか。
Puka-puka.
オッケー！じゃあ正解いきましょう！正解...
Okay! Then let's reveal the answer! The answer is...
Error processing subtitles for this segment.
今日の優勝者を 一応発表しますか
Shall we announce today's winner?
今日はですね、イオフィが優勝でございます、もうほぼ。
Today, Iofi is our winner, pretty much!
わー！やったー！
Yay! I did it!
半分以上正解して。
Having gotten over half of them right.
天才！流石！
Genius! As expected!
天才だ。流石でございます。
A true genius. Just as expected.
いやいやー / 日本語上手！
No, no... / Your Japanese is so good!
日本語上手。でもね、えっと他のメンバーもあれですよ、
So good! But you know, all the other members too,
半分は正解してますから、素晴らしいでございます。
got at least half right, which is wonderful!
おー！やったー！
Ooh! Yay!
ということで、皆さん本日もありがとうございましたー！
And with that, thank you all so much for joining us today!
えー、チャンネル登録もね...
Be sure to subscribe to the channels...
ありがとうございました！ありがとう！
Thank you so much! Thank you!
じゃ、チャンネル登録も... あ！
So, subscribe to the chann— Ah!
あ、ちょっと...
Ah, wait...
ちょ、ちょちょちょ。チャンネル登録の方も...
Wait, wait, wait, hold on! Also, don't forget to...
ポチッとお願いしますね。
click that subscribe button!
はーい！お願いしまーす！
Okay! Please subscribe!
ということで、最後はバイバイで終わっていきますよ。
So, let's wrap things up with a final "Bye-bye!" Ready...
せーの！ / はい！
...set... / Okay!
バイバーイ！
Bye-bye!
チーポン カンポン チーポン カンポン...
Chipon kampon, chipon kampon...
チーポン カンポン ブロンボローン
Chipon kampon, buron-boron~
バイバーイ！
Bye-bye!